Claudia de Lys Papers
Claudia de Lys Papers
1920-1960
Lys, Claudia de.
23 linear ft.
American anthropologist, author. Collection includes correspondence, clippings, drafts and manuscripts for publication, photographs, news releases, printed material. Writings and research material on customs, folklore, palmistry, and superstition.
149420
Biographical History
Claudia de Lys (dates unknown) is an American anthropologist and author of numerous books on customs, folklore, palmistry, and superstition.
Scope and Contents of the Collection
The Claudia de Lys Papers consist of three accessions which have not yet been integrated. The collection has received minimal processing, and the inventory which follows is a simple box listing.
The original accession contains correspondence, galley proofs, and printed material (mostly newspaper and magazine clippings) and a three-part recording of an interview with de Lys.
The 1990 addition contains correspondence, photographs, writings, and memorabilia.
The 1992 addition contains correspondence, writings, and memorabilia.
Arrangement of the Collection
The collection has received minimal processing and by and large remains in original order. Note that the box numbering restarts with "Box 1" for each. Please specify accession and box number when requesting material.
Separated Material
More than one hundred artifacts and pieces of art were transferred to the Syracuse University Art Collection in 1985. These include 27 original cartoons by Ton Smits; 30 drawings, 47 prints and three print blocks by Gus Bundy; a bas-relief bust of de Lys by Edgardo Simone; a charcoal portrait of de Lys by Paul Swan; and an oil painting of the Hagia Sophia in Turkey, circa 1930. For more information about these items please contact the SU Art Galleries.
Subject and Genre Headings
Women Authors; Religion and philosophy; Science and medicine; Lys, Claudia de.; Anthropologists -- United States.; Cats -- Mythology.; Folklore.; Folklorists -- United States.; Manners and customs.; Superstition.; Correspondence.; Clippings (information artifacts); Drafts (documents); Manuscripts for publication.; Phonograph records.; Photographs.; Anthropologists.
Access Restrictions
The majority of our archival and manuscript collections are housed offsite and require advanced notice for retrieval. Researchers are encouraged to contact us in advance concerning the collection material they wish to access for their research.
Acquisition Information
Unspecified, 1990, 1992.
Inventory
- Original accession
  - Correspondence, 1920s-1960s; incoming and outgoing; contains some print material (Box 1)
  - Graphic material, copies of print cartoons by Ton Smits; drawings and block prints by Gus Bundy; originals transferred to SU Art Galleries (Box 2)
  - Graphic material, photographs (Box 3)
  - Galley proofs, A Treasury of Parenthood (Box 4)
  - Galley proofs, A Treasury of American Superstition and To Be or Not To Be a Virgin, also typescript of To Be or Not To Be a Virgin (Box 5)
  - Signatures, unbound, A Treasury of American Superstition (Box 6)
  - Typescripts, ideas for advertiseres; radio program; dictionary of French sayings (Box 6)
  - Printed material, superstitions; typescript copies; news releases; clippings (Box 7)
  - Printed material, typescript list of sayings (Box 8)
  - Printed material, clippings of sayings
    - Air and breathing (Box 9)
    - Breasts (Box 9)
    - Breastfeeding (Box 9)
    - Hands, fingers (Box 10)
    - Handwritings (Box 10)
    - Lefthandedness (Box 10)
    - Palmistry (Box 10)
    - Hands, symbols (Box 11)
    - Mouth, diseases (Box 11)
    - Mouth, falsehoods (Box 11)
    - Mouth, Kinsey Dept. (Box 11)
    - Mouth, kissing (Box 11)
    - Mouth, kissing (Box 12)
    - Mouth, kissing (Box 13)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 14)
  - Printed material, superstition clippings (Box 15)
  - Printed material, superstition clippings (Box 16)
  - Printed material, superstition clippings (Box 17)
  - Printed material, superstition clippings (Box 18)
  - Printed material, scrapbook of clippings
  - Recordings
    - “Superstition In News”, Claudia de Lys, Part 1 and Part 6 (disc 1 of 3), lys_cd_001; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - “Superstition In News”, Claudia de Lys, Part 2 and Part 4 (disc 2 of 3), lys_cd_002; Lacquer discs/acetates
    - “Superstition In News”, Claudia de Lys, Part 3 and Part 5 (disc 3 of 3), lys_cd_003; Lacquer discs/acetates
- 1990 accession
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - Adamo, Hunter and Alice
    - Batchelor, C.D. and Julie Forsyth, includes original artwork
    - Battey, Terence Louise
    - Bundy, Gus, includes original artwork
    - Cloud, Virginia
    - Cole, Madelaine
    - Darragh, Kathleen
    - Debruille, Paulette
    - Evans, Henry S.
    - Evans, Isabelle and Philip
    - Garmisa, Ilyana
    - Grayson, Anka and James
    - Grolier, Inc.
    - Hamilton, Marjorie J.
    - Harcourt, Brace and Company
    - Kamin, Claude and Martin
    - Kendrick, Eleanore (agent)
    - Kilbourn, Lucy
    - Kline, Harry Byrd
    - Lopatecki, Yvonne de
    - Murphy, J.E., includes original artwork
    - Oldfield, Barney
    - Oman, Annie and Sheridan, includes original artwork
    - Orner, Faustina
    - Plantiff, Ellen
    - Poterbaugh, Edward and Celene
    - Russell, George B. and Edith
    - Serebrykoff, Lynn Christensen
    - Short, Marcia
    - Silvermine Publishers
    - Speller, Robert (publisher?)
    - Sugar, Paul
    - Tomiuk, Yolande / Tania Shamy
    - Traver, Marion Gray, includes original artwork
    - Wadler, Leonard
    - White, Mary Lee
  - Photographs
    - Miscellaneous
  - Writings
    - "The Cat is Out of the Bag", manuscript draft
    - Superstitious? Here's Why
    - A Treasury of American Superstition
    - A Treasury of Parenthood and Its Folklore
    - Your Cat: Fact and Superstition
    - Your Cat: A Treasury of Fact and Superstition
  - Memorabilia
    - Clippings
    - Essays
    - Phonodiscs, 2 LPs
    - Syndicate sheets
    - Miscellaneous
- 1992 accession
  - Correspondence-subject files
    - General (Box 1)
    - Personal
      - MacNiel, Stanley S. (Box 1)
      - Mayfield, John, 3 folders (Box 1)
      - Philosophical Library, Inc. (Box 1)
      - Syracuse University (Box 1)
    - Subject files
      - Boy (Box 1)
      - Bundling (Box 1)
      - Chaperons (Box 1)
      - Circumcision (Box 1)
      - Sex determination, 2 folders (Box 1)
  - Writings
    - Books
      - A Century of Cats (Box 1)
    - Essays
      - "As I recall…en route on my life's journey", manuscript draft (Box 1)
      - "As I recall…en route on my life's journey", manuscript draft (Box 2)
      - "The cat's out of the bag" (working title: The Cat's Nine Lives Plus), correspondence, research material, photographs, manuscript drafts (Box 2)
      - "Lena's Odd Odyssey", research material, manuscripts, 4 folders (Box 2)
      - "Savage wife excels as husband's partner," New York World-Telegram, 10 Jan 1935 (Box 2)
      - "Working island cats" Pet Digest Winter 1964 (Box 2)
      - "Your cat: a treasury of fact and superstition, manuscript draft, 2 folders (Box 2)
  - Memorabilia
    - Printed material
      - Clippings about (Box 2)
      - Clippings, general (Box 2)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 2)